Guide to the James Thomas Papers, 1850-1882, bulk 1852-1861 RL.10092
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
James Thomas papers
1850-1879
1852-1861
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Thomas, James
RL.10092
13.5 Linear Feet 26 boxes (14,008 items)
This collection contains business and personal correspondence, orders, price bulletins, and other papers, relating to the tobacco business of James Thomas, the tobacco industry in general, and the economic life of Virginia (1850s). Includes information on Thomas' assistance to the Virginia Baptist Seminary (now the University of Richmond). Correspondents and persons mentioned include J. L. M. Curry, George Frederick Holmes, and Basil Manly.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Biographical Note
James Thomas, Jr. (1813-1882) was a tobacco manufacturer of Richmond, Virginia.
Provenance
The James Thomas Papers were acquired by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 1937.
Collection Overview
This collection consists principally of the apparently complete business papers and records, 1850-1863, of James Thomas, Jr. (1806-1882), one of the largest of antebellum tobacco manufacturers. In addition to an extensive business correspondence, numerous orders for tobacco from Maine, Massachusetts, Louisiana, Georgia, the Netherlands, England, and Australia are included, as well as prices current bulletins from firms throughout the world. The collection not only gives a detailed history of Thomas's enterprises, but affords much information on the tobacco industry in general and on other phases of the economic life of Virginia in the 1850s. Some of Thomas's private correspondence is also in the collection, including an occasional letter from such men as J. L. M. Curry and George Frederick Holmes. Some information is given on Thomas's aid to Basil Manly in his work with the Virginia Baptist Seminary (later the Univesity of Richmond), and on his financial assistance, which made it possible for the institution to remain open after the Civil War.
Virginia -- Economic conditions; Tobacco industry -- Virginia; Tobacco industry -- Records; Industries -- Virginia; Universities and colleges -- Virginia; University of Richmond -- History; Curry, J. L. M. (Jabez Lamar Monroe); Holmes, George Frederick, 1820-1897; Manly, Basil; Virginia Baptist Seminary (Richmond, Va.)
- Correspondence and papers, 1842-September 1852; 6 folders (Box 1)
- Correspondence and papers, October 1852-April 1853; 6 folders (Box 2)
- Correspondence and papers, May - December 1853; 5 folders (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous, undated; 1 folders (Box 3)
- Correspondence and papers, January - July 1854; 7 folders (Box 4)
- Correspondence and papers, August 1854 - February 1855; 7 folders (Box 5)
- Correspondence and papers, March - September 1855; 7 folders (Box 6)
- Correspondence and papers, October 1855 - April 1856; 8 folders (Box 7)
- Correspondence and papers, May - October 1856; 7 folders (Box 8)
- Correspondence and papers, November 1856 - April 1857; 6 folders (Box 9)
- Correspondence and papers, May - October 1857; 6 folders (Box 10)
- Correspondence and papers, November 1857 - March 1858; 5 folders (Box 11)
- Correspondence and papers, April - August 1858; 6 folders (Box 12)
- Correspondence and papers, September - December 1858; 4 folders (Box 13)
- Miscellaneous, 1858; 1 folders (Box 13)
- Correspondence and papers, January - May 1859; 5 folders (Box 14)
- Correspondence and papers, June - October 1859; 5 folders (Box 15)
- Correspondence and papers, November 1859 - March 1860; 5 folders (Box 16)
- Correspondence and papers, April - August 1860; 5 folders (Box 17)
- Correspondence and papers, September - December 1860; 4 folders (Box 18)
- Correspondence and papers, January - June 1861; 6 folders (Box 19)
- Correspondence and papers, July 1861 - December 1862; 6 folders (Box 20)
- Correspondence and papers, 1863-1879; undated; 3 folders (Box 21)
- Virginia receipts, undated; 2 folders (Box 21)
- Virginia receipts, undated; 5 folders (Box 22)
- Virginia receipts, 1855-1862; 7 folders (Box 23)
- Virginia receipts, 1852-1861; 6 folders (Box 24)
- Virginia receipts, 1853-1859; 6 folders (Box 25)
- Virginia receipts, 1854-1861; 6 folders (Box 26)